<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Basically Speaking</title>
    <description>One mistake at a time</description>
    <link>primal.pw</link>
    <atom:link href="primal.pw/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>A Brief note on You and Your Research</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is an attempt to summarize the important points of the talk &amp;lsquo;You and Your Research&amp;rsquo; delivered by &lt;strong&gt;Dr. Richard W Hamming&lt;/strong&gt; at a seminar in the Bell Communications Research Colloquia Series. The talk tries to answer the question of &lt;strong&gt;How to do
first class research&lt;/strong&gt;, the kind of research that fetch nobel prizes and eternal greatness.
As Dr. Hamming himself says at the beginning of the talk &amp;lsquo;It is not about managing research, it is about how you individually do your research.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Great work is not done by luck. The &lt;em&gt;prepared mind&lt;/em&gt; sooner or later finds something important and does it. The particular thing you do is luck, but that you do something is not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have independent thoughts and foster the &lt;em&gt;courage&lt;/em&gt; to pursue them. Once you get your courage up and believe that you can do important problems, then you can. If you think you can&amp;rsquo;t, almost surely you are not going to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Age is not important&lt;/em&gt; in the way you think it is. People always say that you have got to do it when you are young or you will never do it. History has a lot of examples to support this proposition. But what really happens in those examples is that people did some good work when they were young and found themselves on all kinds of committees and being unable to do any more work. When you are famous it is hard to work on small problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What most people think are the best working conditions, are most often not so. People are often most productive when working conditions are bad. The ones you want aren&amp;rsquo;t always the best ones for you. What appears to be a fault, often, by a &lt;em&gt;change of viewpoint&lt;/em&gt;, turns out to be one of the greatest assets you can have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knowledge and productivity&lt;/em&gt; are like compound interest. Given two people of approximately the same ability and one person who works ten percent more than the other, the latter will more than twice outproduce the former. The more you know, the more you learn; the more you learn, the more you can do; the more you can do, the more the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Importance of &lt;em&gt;the trait of ambiguity&lt;/em&gt;. If you believe too much you&amp;rsquo;ll never notice the flaws; if you doubt too much you won&amp;rsquo;t get started. It requires a lovely balance. When you find apparent flaws you&amp;rsquo;ve got to be sensitive and keep track of those things, and keep an eye out for how they can be explained or how the theory can be changed to fit them. Those are often the great contributions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creativity comes out of your subconscious. When you have a real important problem you don&amp;rsquo;t let anything else get the &lt;em&gt;center of your attention&lt;/em&gt; - you keep your thoughts on the problem. Keep your subconscious starved so it has to work on your problem, so you can sleep peacefully and get the answer in the morning, free.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself these questions: What are the &lt;em&gt;important problems&lt;/em&gt; in my field? What important problems am I working on? And most importantly  If what I am doing is not important, and if I don&amp;rsquo;t think it is going to lead to something important, why am I working on it? If you do not work on an important problem, it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely you&amp;rsquo;ll do important work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t always know exactly where to be, but you can &lt;em&gt;keep active&lt;/em&gt; in places where something might happen. Stand on a mountain top where lightning strikes; you don&amp;rsquo;t have to hide in the valley where you&amp;rsquo;re safe. Think hard hard about where your field is going, where were the opportunities, and what were the important things to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keep your door open while working&lt;/em&gt;. You might be less productive than the one who keeps the door closed due to all kinds of interruptions. But occassionally one gets clues as to what the world is and what might be important. The closed door is symbolic of a closed mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It ain&amp;rsquo;t what you do, it&amp;rsquo;s the way that you do it&lt;/em&gt;. By changing the question around, you can do important work rather than trivial work. Obey Newton&amp;rsquo;s rule and climb up the shoulders of giants and see further than they did. Instead of solving isolated problems, work on building solutions that others can build on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is not sufficient to do a job, you have to sell it&lt;/em&gt;.  You have to learn to write clearly and well so that people will read it, you must learn to give reasonably formal talks, and you also must learn to give informal talks. In cases where you haven&amp;rsquo;t got control on what you have to work on, it means you are not selling ideas to the top management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of talk Dr.Hamming explains why people with great promises sometimes fail inspite of being better equipped to do productive work. The following points outlines &lt;strong&gt;the ingredients for becoming a first class researcher according to him.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drive and Commitment. Outstanding work requires outstanding commitment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to work with the system and take advantage of all what it has to offer. You have to choose between reforming the system or doing first class science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at the positive side of things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He concludes his talk by saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The reasons why many people who have greatness within their grasp don&amp;rsquo;t succeed are:
they don&amp;rsquo;t work on important problems,
they don&amp;rsquo;t become emotionally involved,
they don&amp;rsquo;t try and change what is difficult to some other situation which is easily done but is still important,
and they keep giving themselves alibis why they don&amp;rsquo;t.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this post inspires to do first class work in whatever field you are. This is not an exact subsitute for reading the entire transcript of the talk and I would recommend that you do that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.csee.umbc.edu/~finin/YouAndYourResearch.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if time permits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.csee.umbc.edu/~finin/home/&quot;&gt;Dr. Tim Finin&lt;/a&gt;, Professor at
Department of Computer Science, University of Maryland at Baltimore County, for posting the transcript of talk on his home page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/general/2012/08/24/a-brief-note-on-you-and-your-research/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/general/2012/08/24/a-brief-note-on-you-and-your-research/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Droidcon India 2011</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Undocumented memories fade away and some of the memories are too valuable to let them
escape into the oblivion. This post is the documentation of my experience at &lt;a href=&quot;http://droidcon.in/2011/&quot;&gt;Droidcon India&lt;/a&gt; which
happened at Bangalore in November 2011. By laying out in words, I am hoping to preserve the  memory
of an amazing experience I had at the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://primux.in/projects/2012/02/06/summer-of-11-story-of-my-gsoc-application/&quot;&gt;summer of 2011&lt;/a&gt;, I was busy coding &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.mobile-accessibility.idrc.ocad.ca/w/Tagin!&quot;&gt;tagin!&lt;/a&gt; which is an Indoor Location
Tagging Engine for Android. Towards the end of Google Summer of Code 2011, I came across the
announcement of Call for Papers(CFP) for first ever International Android conference in India,
Droidcon 2011. It was organized by the awesome folks at &lt;a href=&quot;http://hasgeek.com/&quot;&gt;hasgeek&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/blrdroid/&quot;&gt;Bangalore Android User&amp;rsquo;s Group&lt;/a&gt;.
They had come up with an ingenious way of selecting talks for the conference. Basically, all the submitted
talks were added to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://funnel.hasgeek.com/droidcon/&quot;&gt;funnel&lt;/a&gt; and talks with highest number of votes was considered for
review  by expert panel and afterwards selected for presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As luck had it, &lt;a href=&quot;http://funnel.hasgeek.com/droidcon/70-indoor-location-tagging-engine&quot;&gt;my proposed talk&lt;/a&gt; got a healthy number of upvotes. Few days after the
deadline for CFP when the &lt;a href=&quot;http://droidcon.in/2011/schedule/&quot;&gt;schedule of the conference&lt;/a&gt; came out,
my talk was part of it. I was ecstatic(rightly so) but nervous as well because conference was happening
just 3 days away from my GRE exam. But this was an opportunity which I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to miss hence I
decided to go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the presentation was about something I had worked on, making slides was easy.
The tougher part was to find analogues to explain some of the concepts used in the project.
My GSoC mentor, Jorge Silva&amp;rsquo;s feedback was very helpful in this aspect. He also gave
some invaluable insight on how to refine the slides and make my presentation better. You can see the slides I used
for the talk here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:425px&quot; id=&quot;__ss_13530424&quot;&gt;&lt;strong style=&quot;display:block;margin:12px 0 4px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/primal007/droidcon-primal-13530424&quot; title=&quot;Droidcon primal&quot;&gt;Droidcon &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;object id=&quot;__sse13530424&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot;&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;movie&quot; value=&quot;http://static.slidesharecdn.com/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=droidconprimal-120703133919-phpapp01&amp;stripped_title=droidcon-primal-13530424&amp;userName=primal007&quot; /&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;allowFullScreen&quot; value=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;allowScriptAccess&quot; value=&quot;always&quot;/&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;wmode&quot; value=&quot;transparent&quot;/&gt;&lt;embed name=&quot;__sse13530424&quot; src=&quot;http://static.slidesharecdn.com/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=droidconprimal-120703133919-phpapp01&amp;stripped_title=droidcon-primal-13530424&amp;userName=primal007&quot; type=&quot;application/x-shockwave-flash&quot; allowscriptaccess=&quot;always&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; wmode=&quot;transparent&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon reaching Bangalore, I straightaway headed to where my friends were staying in Bangalore.
They were generous to accomodate me at their place and sponsor my dinner for all the three days
I had stayed there.  Having been previously to Bangalore, I knew about the crazy traffic jams there,
but never would have guessed it would take around 2.5 hours to cover 30 kms.The ordeal of a long train journey in
the previous night coupled with this experience started to take it&amp;rsquo;s toll. Therefore after watching few talks, I skipped the
evening party and headed back to catch some sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7003/6393426149_ae32e1e60a_n.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next day, I was better prepared and started early for the conference. This time I reached the venue
in flat 30 mins even before the Organizers had turned up. My talk was scheduled in the afternoon,
therefore I attended some of the talks that was happening in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My talk started at 1.45 and contrary to my expectations, a lot of people had turned up. :)
I ended up taking the entire 45 minute slot for presenting my work, leaving no time for Q and A.
Talking to some startup guys after my presentation I came to know that few others
were working on a similar products as well. All in all, my first talk at an International Conference
went well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the day, I roamed around in the Garden city. I also went to Blossoms book shop which was famous
for selling second hand books at very low prices. With a bag full of books and mind full of good memories
I boarded the train back to Thrissur.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jul 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/conference/2012/07/04/droidcon-india-2011/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/conference/2012/07/04/droidcon-india-2011/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PyCon Asia Pacific 2012</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;http://primux.in/General/2011/09/09/salaam-bombay/&quot;&gt;one of the earlier
posts&lt;/a&gt;, I am presently at IIT Bombay working
as a Research Assistant in the Free and Open Source Software for Indian
Engineering Education(FOSSEE) project. Earlier on in March we, myself and
Parth Buch(FOSSEEmate) dared to do something that was very ambitious. We
submitted a talk proposal at PyCon Asia Pacific(APAC) 2012
which was happening at Singapore. The topic of the talk was &amp;ldquo;FOSSEE:
Pythonizing the Indian Engineering Education&amp;rdquo;. Much to our surprise, we found
that &lt;a href=&quot;http://apac.pycon.org/2012/w/page/talks#talk_24&quot;&gt;our talk&lt;/a&gt; was selected
when the schedule was out in the mid of May. But with the kind of expenses
involved for travel and accomodation, going to Singapore for the conference
looked improbable. Thanks to the support from Prof.
Madhu Belur and IRCC office at IIT Bombay we finally had sufficient funds to go for the
conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was our first travel across the borders and we both underestimated the
things to be done before the trip. At the cost of sacrificing sleep on the
penultimate day we could get most of the important things out of the
way(Insurance, Accomodation, International Travel card, Singapore sim card).
Finally on June 5th early morning we took off from CSI Airport Mumbai to Singapore. After
touching down at Changi Airport we straightaway went to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hostelworld.com/hosteldetails.php/Fernloft-East-Coast/Singapore/7770?source=adwordsdynamic&amp;amp;kid=569286&amp;amp;aid=2&amp;amp;gclid=COWaroW16bACFUcb6wod0kGqzA&quot;&gt;Fernloft,
Eastcoast&lt;/a&gt;
where we had booked a dorm earlier. That day evening and the next day was
mostly spent in sleeping and preparing for the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 6th morning, we got up early in the morning and took the train to
Woodlands where, Republic Poly Technique, the venue of conference was located.
Morning was spent in attending the tutorial on &lt;a href=&quot;http://apac.pycon.org/2012/w/page/tutorials#tut_9&quot;&gt;Big Data
Analysis&lt;/a&gt;.
In the afternoon we got out and went to Little India(India within Singapore) to have some
Indian food which we have been craving since last 3 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 8th, second day of the conference we reached early to catch the
keynote of Alex Martelli on &amp;ldquo;Permission and Forgiveness&amp;rdquo;. Afterwards we
attended some good talks like &amp;ldquo;Python and the Web&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Fun with Iterators and
Generators&amp;rdquo; etc before our talk was up in the evening. The audience for our
talk was lower than what we had expected but those who were present actively asked doubts and
gave suggestions on where to improve. It was interesting to know that the
countries(Singapore, Europe, US)  where the people in the audience belonged to
had no similar projects to promote Python or Free and Open Source Software(FOSS).
Few of them offered their support in creating Spoken Tutorials and a lady from
Singapore Education Department talked to us a long time afterwards on
implementing some of the projects in their educational ecosystem. The full talk
can be seen below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/SAXAz2EeVMg&quot;
frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Slides used for the talk can be seen
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/primal007/pythonizing-the-indian-engineering-education&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you wish to see other talks
at PyCon APAC, heres the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/user/pyconapac?feature=results_main&quot;&gt;playlist of
talks&lt;/a&gt; presented at the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback on this video has been amazing until now.
The PyCon APAC experience gave me the insight that our work at FOSSEE would be useful
just not for Indian Engineering students but also for people from other countries
as well who are interested to know and learn about FOSS and Python. As promised
in the video we are working on getting the web application for Spoken Tutorials
ready which would make the experience of learing much more interactive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading and please feel free to leave your feedback as comments
to this post or on the youtube video.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/conference/2012/06/25/pycon-2012-asia-pacific/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/conference/2012/06/25/pycon-2012-asia-pacific/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Golden age of creativity: Savouring while it lasts</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My contention is that these days we live in right now will be looked back on
with longing, especially with various governments trying to push through laws
to control the internet. If that happens, these will be the good old days, so
don’t take them for granted. Look around and enjoy. I think this is an
incredible time to make things, and I hope it stays around for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terry Border of Bent Objects&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few days back, I watched the movie &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1605783/&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Midnight in
Paris&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by Woody Allen.
The protagonist of the movie always wished to travel back in time to Paris of
the 1930s, which for him, was the golden age of creativity. And
suddenly he was in 1930(no questions asked) with Ernest Hemingway and the
alike, he discovers that the people of that time wished to be a part of 1890s
which they considered as the golden age. Its an alright movie, but it had a
brilliant point well put forward that people dont realize themselves being part
of golden age, its generation afterwards that discovers it. Then its
too late already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have seen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1166827/&quot;&gt;Zeitgeist&lt;/a&gt;, you already know the fallacies of the &amp;lsquo;real world&amp;rsquo;
we are part of. By taking down the World Trade Center and 10,000 lives, US
government made sure that it could take control of the life of their citizens
completely. The more I look around, I realize that world is driven forward by
fear rather than love. This is ideal for governments and religious dogmas,
which strive to divide people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does that leave us? In the &amp;lsquo;real world&amp;rsquo; where the freedom is defined the
very insitutions that deny it, lets roll over to the Virtual world -
&lt;strong&gt;Internet&lt;/strong&gt; which on virtue of its lack of structure and centralized control has
largely remained free in the real free sense. &lt;a href=&quot;http://smedio.com/2011/02/04/how-twitter-is-helping-with-the-egyptian-revolution/&quot;&gt;Dictators have
fallen&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://wikileaks.org/&quot;&gt;fallacies have been exposed&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.nationalpost.com/2012/01/20/sopa-stopped-after-unprecedented-online-protests/&quot;&gt;evil plots have been
thwarted&lt;/a&gt;
through this medium of speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Governments are trying hard
to instill fear upon the netizens by taking down that World Trade Center of the
online world and forcing people to surrender their freedom in return for security.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_Online_Piracy_Act&quot;&gt;SOPA&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PROTECT_IP_Act&quot;&gt;PIPA&lt;/a&gt; may have failed now but with ever reducing attention span of the
people, the US government is sure to pull it through in the second or third
time. Soon other countries will follow suit and together with &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204542404577158342623999990.html#ixzz1jVPdAsNT&quot;&gt;various
censorships&lt;/a&gt;, Internet as we know will cease to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before all that happens, realize for yourself that we are part of a golden age of
creativity and it is not going to last forever. Savour the freedom while it
lasts by enjoying what we have and excercising the right of opinion. Let me end
this soliloquy with a quote from Zeitgiest,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The most incredible aspect of all: these totalitarian elements will not be
forced on people, the people will demand them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/soliloquy/2012/02/18/golden-age-of-creativity-savouring-while-it-lasts/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/soliloquy/2012/02/18/golden-age-of-creativity-savouring-while-it-lasts/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Summer of 11: Story of my Google Summer of Code application</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is that time of the year
&lt;a href=&quot;http://google-opensource.blogspot.in/2012/02/google-summer-of-code-2012-is-on.html&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;, when students all around the world are given an unique opportunity by Google to contribute to an Open Source Project over
the summer. Initially I thought of writing a &lt;strong&gt;How to apply for Google Summer
of Code(GSoC)&lt;/strong&gt; guide at this time
but Internet has too
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sarathlakshman.com/2011/03/28/how-to-apply-for-google-summer-of-code-a-byte-of-note/&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;
of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vaidikkapoor.info/2011/12/gsoc-2012/&quot;&gt;them&lt;/a&gt; already. Hence I settled upon writing this story of
my GSoC application during 2011 hoping to share my memorable experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Genesis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing Google Summer of code had been
a long cherished dream from when I first knew about it in undergraduate studies. But when the
program was announced in early February of 2011, I was in my usual
&lt;strong&gt;busy-doing-nothing&lt;/strong&gt; mode to notice it. Time flew by, it was mid march and I
was in a very bad and desperate mood owing to end of college days nearing(final year student at that time)
when the list of selected organizations for GSoC 2011 came out. Realizing that
it was my last chance at glory, I made up my mind to apply to at least one
project even though time was not on my side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most painful process of finding out a suitable project, ensued. After days of reading through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/accepted_orgs/google/gsoc2011&quot;&gt;organization
and project
pages&lt;/a&gt;, I filtered out some projects based on the intersection of
skills on my resume and requirements of the project. Having done a &lt;a href=&quot;http://primalpop.wordpress.com/2010/09/21/cygnus-microblogging-platform-for-android/&quot;&gt;decent mini
project&lt;/a&gt; in Android in the previous year, I looked out for projects which
sported that keyword in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Exodus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hanging around in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat&quot;&gt;IRC&lt;/a&gt; channels of the chosen organizations was my next
logical move. Even though, I hardly said anything in these channels during this
time, it helped me to figure out the already set pool of applicants and evaluate my chances of making the
cut for that project. Owing to extreme delay(march-end) in my start of proceedings, some of the
projects already had a large number of prospective applicants. After few days
of reading, I settled upon &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.komodoopenlab.com/index.php/Main/GSoC2011#toc6&quot;&gt;Indoor Geocaching game project by Komodo Open
Lab&lt;/a&gt;
for applying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After being the silent observer in various IRC channels previously, I decided to get into action
straightaway in the IRC channel for this project. Blurting out the details of
my interest in the project, I waited for a response. After a few minutes of
silence, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Czn0Cn3OmPo&amp;amp;lr=1&quot;&gt;Jorge Silva&lt;/a&gt;(my future mentor) asked whether we could talk over skype the details of
project. For someone who was expecting only a minimal text response, this was a
jackpot. He talked to me in length about the project idea and encouraged me to
apply asap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Chronicles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until that moment, GSoC was feeling like a distant dream but now I was in
with a chance. This motivated me to go on full throttle. After working for a
continous stretch of 9 hours I was up with what can be called a beta version of the
project proposal and mailed to Jorge. This happened before the real application
process began in April and gave me some much needed leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having almost completed the application left me with nothing to do until April
end when results would be announced. I started brainstorming for further ideas to be
implemented on the application and documenting them in the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.mobile-accessibility.idrc.ocad.ca/w/User_talk:Primalpop&quot;&gt;Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. I took it up
as a challenge to have something new to show on the wiki on at least every alternate
day. Nights were spent in IRC discussing the brainwaves I had earlier
in the day(if any). Being the wonderful guy he is, Jorge
always listened to my ideas patiently and pointed out the flaws and fine points
in them. Over this period the abstract ideas were refined out and this also aided
in improving my application. When I was without ideas, I asked plainly what
could I do for the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Judgement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I submitted my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/proposal/review/google/gsoc2011/primalpop/1&quot;&gt;final
application&lt;/a&gt; one week before the deadline and was pretty
satisfied about it. Just after the deadline, upon my inquiry Jorge told in IRC
that there were 3 slots and 17 applicants for them that year. This
was a wake up call for me and I realized a good application can take me only so
far. I needed something to distuinguish myself from others. The solution was
staring down at me from the alpha version of the application source code Jorge
had pushed to Launchpad earlier in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next weekend was spent in reading the source code and understanding how the
application worked. Not having a phone handicapped me from testing the
app and &lt;a href=&quot;http://pramode.net&quot;&gt;Mr. Pramode C E&lt;/a&gt;, my FOSS guru, was kind enough to lent me his phone for
the purpose. But testing involved a lot of repetitive work which could be
automated and I sat down to code a &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.launchpad.net/~primal007/tagin/tagin-inplace&quot;&gt;Logger for the
app&lt;/a&gt; which would esentially
run the app in an infinite loop and store the various readings in CSV format.
Few days before the results were announced I pushed the code into a seperate
branch of launchpad and thus I had that something powerful and substantial to aid my application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day of results arrived and by this time I had fallen in love with the project
and had made up my mind to contribute irrespective of whether I was selected for
GSoC or not.  As I had no idea of how the results would be announced, I was
lingering around in IRC channels chatting to other applicants who had already become my
friends over the one month period. At 12 in midnight, Carol posted in gsoc irc channel
that results had been sent out to applicants. I waited nervously with seconds
feeling like hours. Finally at 12.30 I received a mail in my inbox which read like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dear Primal,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! Your proposal &amp;ldquo;Indoor Geocaching game&amp;rdquo; as submitted to Komodo
OpenLab Inc. has been accepted for Google Summer of Code 2011.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went numb with happyness. The month long ordeal had paid its
dividends in full. Thus began the open source adventure and wonderful summer of
coding, which taught me so many things that it wouldnt be an exaggeration if I said it was life
changing because it really was. :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The completion of Google Summer of Code convinced me that higher education
was the way to go and only research would satiate my urge to know more. Dropping other job offers, I joined IIT Bombay as a Research
Assistant in FOSSEE project with a plan to apply for higher studies in the next
fall. I was also chosen to speak at &lt;a href=&quot;http://droidcon.in/2011/&quot;&gt;First
International Android Conference in India&lt;/a&gt;, which
happened at Bangalore, on &lt;a href=&quot;http://funnel.hasgeek.com/droidcon/70-indoor-location-tagging-engine&quot;&gt;Indoor Location Tagging Engine&lt;/a&gt;.
Also, my name was mentioned in the coveted &lt;a href=&quot;http://google-opensource.blogspot.in/2011/07/whos-new-in-google-summer-of-code-part_22.html&quot;&gt;Google Open
Source Blog&lt;/a&gt;
as part of introducing Komodo Open Lab to GSoC 2011. Now thats something, isnt
it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;P.S&lt;/em&gt;: My contributions(through code) to the FOSS world was very minimal
while applying. A couple of personal projects and a decent
stackoverflow reputation were the mention worthy items in my resume at that
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;P.P.S&lt;/em&gt;: Due to frequent nighouts and infrequent eating, I had lost nearly 6
kilograms of weight with no excercise at all during the application period.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/projects/2012/02/06/summer-of-11-story-of-my-gsoc-application/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/projects/2012/02/06/summer-of-11-story-of-my-gsoc-application/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Salaam Bombay</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post has been cooking for a long time, too long that even I forgot at times that it was on the gas.  I have prepared to spill the beans and publish this post today and thereby overcome my obsession with delaying everything for betterment. So yes, I am in Bombay and to be exact in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iitb.ac.in/&quot;&gt;IIT Powai&lt;/a&gt;. I a Research Assisstant in Free and Open Source Software in Science and Engineering(&lt;a href=&quot;http://fossee.in&quot;&gt;fossee&lt;/a&gt;) project in the Aerospace Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing my undergraduate studies I was confused about my immediate commitment  between job and higher studies. I knew deep down that once I joined a company, it would be hard for me to break out of the system and pursue my higher studies at a latter point of time. That&amp;rsquo;s when &lt;a href=&quot;http://pramode.net&quot;&gt;Pramode&lt;/a&gt; Sir, my teacher and guide introduced me to FOSSEE and after few days of thought I was certain that it should be my calling. After one week of goodbyes and packaging, I flew to Bombay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had huge expectations of the place and so I was here even before my &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/soc/&quot;&gt;GSoC&lt;/a&gt; project got over because I felt that the IIT atmosphere would be more conductive to work than being at home. But it was far away from a smooth ride after reaching IIT. The first of the  problems was accomodation. I had to move around with my luggage to some 5 rooms during a period of 3 weeks before I got settled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The food was the second calamity. The mouth watering mess menu was a hoax and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gymkhana.iitb.ac.in/~tansa/&quot;&gt;Tansa&lt;/a&gt; hostel mess was worst of all the 15 hostels in IIT. Until reaching here, I never knew I would miss food at home so badly and my mother&amp;rsquo;s constant pushing to eat at time. Language problem was significant barrier too. Even though I had learned 8 years of Hindi at school, I can hardly speak the language. I can understand what people say, but I get stuck when I try to reply in Hindi back to them. The underlying fact, that I was staying away from the home for the first time magnified my miseries and at one point I even thought of returning back to my home. But giving up was never an option. ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After almost an month of survival, most of the problems stands resolved now and I got one of the better rooms in Tansa and a likeable but slightly lunatic roomie. I chose to ate food from the canteen and stuck to a constant dish to save my stomach from getting used to problems. Language problem still persists but my inhibition to speak hindi has reduced much and I can get by with English at most places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at the past one month, I am happy that I had to face all these problems because I made some good friends during the period of crisis. My college mate Alex Poovathingal&amp;rsquo;s presence was always comforting and Fossee team members especially Anand Ramachandran and Deepak Kharat in spite of having to suffer my constant whining, were always helpful and understanding. Principal Investigators of the project, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aero.iitb.ac.in/~prabhu/&quot;&gt;Prof. Prabhu Ramachandran&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ee.iitb.ac.in/wiki/faculty/belur&quot;&gt;Prof. Madhu Belur&lt;/a&gt; were very friendly and gave me ample freedom and time to complete my gsoc project. There are lot of other people who also helped me either through comforting words(calls/chat) or by friendly demeanor at various points during my stay at Mumbai.  Even though I have not mentioned them my name in this post for fear of missing anyone, I would like to thank each of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the few times, I had gone out of IIT, to the outside city of rush and chaos I understood the spirit that drives Mumbaikars despite frequent blasts and a population density that the infrastructure(of the city) can barely contain. Like one of famous phrases in business world &amp;lsquo;The show must go on&amp;rsquo;, the city and it&amp;rsquo;s people never stops and the show goes on with an indomitable spirit that can never be subdued by fear.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2011 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/general/2011/09/09/salaam-bombay/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/general/2011/09/09/salaam-bombay/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mastering the Art of Procrastination</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;First let me apologize if I got you on the wrong foot. This post isn&amp;rsquo;t about how to master procastination but it&amp;rsquo;s rather about how I learned the art of procrastination during the last four years as an undergraduate student at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://universityofcalicut.info&quot;&gt;University of Calicut&lt;/a&gt;. I can safely presume this is the experience of thousands of students who were lucky enough to study here. As you may have guessed already this isn&amp;rsquo;t a direct course offered by the  University but comes as an added bonus irrespective of the course a students enrolls to. So most probably joining this university for higher studies would mean that one will eventually find the dragon scroll for a being a Pro(crastinator).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://selfempowermentsecrets.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/procrastination.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universityofcalicut.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=12&amp;amp;Itemid=336&quot;&gt;University of Calicut&lt;/a&gt; is one of most sought after universities in the state of Kerala with 25 Departments of postgraduate studies and research, under its direct control and 191 affiliated colleges spread across the five northern districts of Kerala–Kozhikode, Malappuram, Palakkad, Thrissur and Wayanad – serving about 2.75 lakh students every year. That&amp;rsquo;s one impressive statistic if you ask me. The only problem comes with the Examination system of the University. Over the years it had the most profound impact on bringing out the best procrastination skills in students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;strong&gt;well defined procedure &lt;/strong&gt;for how the University conducts or rather announces the examinations. There are many unwritten rules(uw) which guide the conductance of these exams. (I wonder why these are unwritten yet as I found only these to be strictly followed by the University.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;First an exam is declared through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universityofcalicut.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=744&amp;amp;Itemid=324&quot;&gt;a notification in the website&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the times it would be when students of other universities are waiting for their results.  As an unwritten rule this happens 3 weeks before the examinations. I guess this is supposed to reduce the trauma of students by letting them know early of the crisis ahead. Here starts a period of procrastination and speculation which ends with examination &amp;ldquo;really&amp;rdquo; starting off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universityofcalicut.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=745&amp;amp;Itemid=325&quot;&gt;Timetable for the examinations&lt;/a&gt; comes a week after the notification. This should ideally get the blood flowing into the brains. Of course it does, but for other reasons. The speculation of whether the exam would be postponed begins and this soon ends with a positive result. The only remaining question is Why? Really interesting theories come up of why it should be postponed. From the death of Osama Bin Laden to local political thug being attacked, everything counts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Next few days, everyone will be busy scouring through every page in the newspaper for the reason of postponement or discussing with their friends in other colleges. Finally after a lot of brainstorming and researching, probable reasons would be churned out. These candidate reasons spread from college to college and it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be long before everyone(maybe except those who scheduled exams) know why exams wouldn&amp;rsquo;t take place on the declared date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the first exam date would collide &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hartal&quot;&gt;Harthal&lt;/a&gt; declared by any political party making it easier for students as well as the University to know why it would be postponed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly it would be because of the conflicts within the University. For example, Suppose the Semester 8 supplementary exam results are yet to be announced(after having conducted them ages ago) and this would mean the students who fail in this exam cannot take part in the examinations already declared. Another example of internal conflict/complexity would be when the Interzone(College Youth Festival) date falls on the same date. Now the very reasonable question why doesn&amp;rsquo;t those who schedule examinations overlook these facts? I would rather answer whether chicken or egg came first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would call the period following the announcement of timetable to when the exam is really postponed &amp;lsquo;the suspense period&amp;rsquo;. It really is, considering how unreliable our politicians and administrators are. Most of us would wait until 2-3 days before exam before giving up hope of postponement. Brave hearted souls would battle till the penultimate day before hitting the books and cursing the university.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now when does the University actually postpone the Examination. It can happen anytime. There has been an instance in which the exams of Production Engineering students were postponed after they were in the exam hall. They were informed after sitting in the exam hall for about 1 hour(without the question paper of course) that the exams were postponed. In very extreme cases, it can get postponed(or better call cancelled) even after students have written the exam and the reasons(once it was because the question paper for the exam was the same as of that a previous year) given would make you bang your head to death. Now as a probable solution if someone considered contacting the University on their given number , you will greeted with either a busy tone or long period of ringing with none picking up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With lots of holidays in between exams it would take at least 3 weeks to complete 5 exams. That gives an estimate how &amp;lsquo;quick&amp;rsquo; it gets over once it&amp;rsquo;s started and it&amp;rsquo;s not surprising that it takes nearly 5 years for obtaining an undergraduate degree from the University. Examination results are always delayed and a mess. You never know what&amp;rsquo;s the University got in store for you with results. With revaluations taking over one year to complete(and considering the history of University&amp;rsquo;s paper valuing theatrics) most would accept failure as their destiny even though deep down they knew they had written the exams well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that I am  cutting it short as I am under the danger of procrastination myself now by writing this post.  Please leave your feedback on the post in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/general/2011/05/16/mastering-the-art-of-procrastination/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/general/2011/05/16/mastering-the-art-of-procrastination/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is it really by the people?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We all proudly say that ours is a democratic country and the leaders who rule us are chosen by us. It&amp;rsquo;s true to an extent, that through elections we choose our government. Elections ensure that it is indeed from the people and for the people but how much is it by the people. Certain statistics will reveal an interesting truth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sticking with &lt;strong&gt;Kerala&lt;/strong&gt; state assembly elections for this analysis; mainly because the most interesting results came out in this state and marginally because its my state. UDF did win over the opposition and will form the government. But how many people did really want an UDF government for the next 5 years? Well, the best way to answer this question is analysing the facts and that&amp;rsquo;s what I am going to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Census India 2011, the population in Kerala is &lt;em&gt;3,33,87,677&lt;/em&gt; or nearly &lt;em&gt;3.33&lt;/em&gt; crores. Now Indian Constitution doesn&amp;rsquo;t let all of these people to cast their votes. A voting age i.e a minimum age established by law that a person must attain to be eligible to vote in a public election, in India is &lt;em&gt;18&lt;/em&gt;. The fate of Kerala would be decided by the &lt;em&gt;2.31&lt;/em&gt; crores of eligible voters. But not everyone of those who are eligible did exercise their civic duty. The average polling percentage in Kerala was &lt;em&gt;74.5%&lt;/em&gt;. This is relatively than some other states in India but considering the high literacy rate(94.59%) in Kerala this should not be the case. Now translating the percentage into numbers, we come to conclusion that 1,72,09,500 voters did cast their votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now turning our focus onto the results of the election, UDF won &lt;em&gt;72&lt;/em&gt; seats out of the total &lt;em&gt;140&lt;/em&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s just one more than &lt;em&gt;71&lt;/em&gt; required for the majority. Going into share of votes, UDF got  80,02,854 (80 lakhs) votes which is &lt;em&gt;46.03&lt;/em&gt; percent of the total vote share and the main opposition party got &lt;em&gt;78,34,334&lt;/em&gt; (78.3 lakh) votes which turns out to be &lt;em&gt;45.06&lt;/em&gt;% of the vote share. That&amp;rsquo;s a meagre &lt;em&gt;34.6&lt;/em&gt;% of the total votes(considering all the eligible voters). Only one out of every three Keralite voted for the soon-to-be ruling government. How can we call this &amp;ldquo;by the people&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you thought I am against democracy, you got it completely wrong. I am a firm supporter of the democratic process and will continue to be. But these facts shows a very sad aspect of democracy in our state and the scene at national level isn&amp;rsquo;t much different too. The solution doesn&amp;rsquo;t lie in changing the system but rather the mindset of the voters.  I don&amp;rsquo;t suggest that everyone should vote for the same party but everyone should indeed vote and be a part of the democratic process. But it should not be the only duty of a citizen during the five years to the nation rather it should be the first step. Voice your concerns, protests, suggestions either online or offline and make sure the government knows it. Thus let&amp;rsquo;s have a democracy in it&amp;rsquo;s full meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.prokerala.com/kerala/population.htm&quot;&gt;http://www.prokerala.com/kerala/population.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://politicskerala.com/kerala-election-2011-polling-percentage-constituancy-wise/&quot;&gt;http://politicskerala.com/kerala-election-2011-polling-percentage-constituancy-wise/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sify.com/news/live-kerala-election-results-news-editors-picks-lfmr4oaffeb.html&quot;&gt;http://www.sify.com/news/live-kerala-election-results-news-editors-picks-lfmr4oaffeb.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer : The author&amp;rsquo;s interest lies in the analysis of statistics and not with any of the political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2011 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/general/2011/05/14/is-it-really-by-the-people/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/general/2011/05/14/is-it-really-by-the-people/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Parsing JSON in Android</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the college mini project,  I along with my group, developed a
micro-blogging platform for Android. One of the biggest hurdles I had to face
was of choosing the proper data format for receiving responses from the web
service. I needed something that was fast as well as easy to understand and
parse.  I first chose XML as it was easy to read and mostly because I knew no
other alternatives. But parsing XML certainly wasnt easy. With the variety of
tags in the responses from the server and the heaviness of XML format, it just
became impossible to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.json.org/fatfree.html&quot;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;(JavaScript Object Notation) came up as an alternative to XML. I was circumspect about using JSON at first as I had doubts about its readability and ease of deserialization. But those doubts were not much more than just superstitions. JSON is smaller and easier to parse, than it&amp;rsquo;s XML equivalent. Many say its less readable than XML, but considering it was used for data interchange, readability was not important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to parse JSON and convert to POJO (Plain Old Java Objects) in Android is to use the Google&amp;rsquo;s GSON library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Download GSON&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the latest Google GSON library from &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/google-gson/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Add this library into your Android Project as an external by right clicking on the desired project and do the following&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Properties -&gt; Java Build Path -&gt; Libraries -&gt; Add External JARs and point to the downloaded gson library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is an array of JSON Objects.  You have to develop a class structure in accordance with the structure of the JSON response received.  For the above example I had the class structure based on the following logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;posts&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;post&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;username&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;John&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m back&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;time&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;2010-5-6 7:00:34&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}},&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;post&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;username&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Smith&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;I&amp;#39;ve been waiting&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;time&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;2010-4-6 10:30:26&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}}]}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;posts&amp;rdquo; data structure contain multiple posts, each of which contains an &amp;ldquo;post&amp;rdquo; type. In order to match this structure, I need to have 3 classes namely PostList, PostContainer and Posts. The PostList class should have an ArrayList of objects of type PostContainer. PostContainer needs just one field which is an object of type Posts. Posts classes must have  3 fields namely username, message and time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;PostList&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostContainer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostContainer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostContainer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;getPostContainterList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;PostContainer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Posts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Posts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;getPost&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Posts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Deserialization Part&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s get into the real business of Deserialization. Using GSON this can be done very easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, import the Google gson library into the class in which JSON String is to be deserialized&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;com.google.gson.Gson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am initializing an ArrayList which contains objects of type Posts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Posts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mObjectList&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ArrayList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Posts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This can be latter on used for adding the Posts objects after deserialization is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jsonString&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Insert your JSON Data here&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instantiate an Object of type PostList&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostList&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;getPostList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jsonString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following function deserializes JSON response to an Object of type PostList and returns it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;protected&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostList&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;getPostList&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jsonString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostList&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pl&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Gson&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gson&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GSON&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pl&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;fromJson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jsonString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What the function getPostList does is, it creates an object of type GSON and deserialize the JSON String to POJO using that object(gson).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;gson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;fromJson&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;jsonString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first parameter to the function is the JSON String and second parameter is the name of the class to which it should be deserialized. Two important things have to be taken care of while using GSON to parse JSON&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tags in JSON String and name of fields of the respective classes should match exactly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Object hierarchy should be built correctly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Failure to comply to the both conditions above would result in some or all of the fields of the classes being left null.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having parsed the JSON string to POJO, we can get various Posts objects separately and add it to the ArrayList which we created earlier as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostContainer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;post_list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getPostContainterList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PostContainer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;post_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;++)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;post_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mObjectList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getPost&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This ArrayList can be used to populate a custom list view. If you have any doubts regarding this post, feel free to ask through comments. In the next post, I will post an tutorial on how to build a custom listview which looks the twitter timeline efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2010 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/android/2010/06/05/parsing-json-in-android/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/android/2010/06/05/parsing-json-in-android/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>First few Steps in Android</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Android has been out for a while now. Although I had heard about Android from various corners a long ago, I didn&amp;rsquo;t take an interest to learn it initially. Two months ago, on accident by purpose, as part of college mini project I decided to develop an application for Android.  Now having jumped into the bandwagon, I feel I should have done the same earlier, but better late than never.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Android is an operating system and software stack for mobile devices and uses a modified version of the Linux Kernel.  Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.android.com/about/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to read more. A big plus for Android is,  coding is done in Java which is one of the most popular programming languages out. Having a good knowledge of Java simplified things for me greatly. If you are new to Java &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.otherwise.com/Lessons/Introducton.html&quot;&gt;this online tutorial&lt;/a&gt; can get you started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pros of Developing for Android&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;No restrictions on applications that can be published.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get to code in Java which is widely known.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can develop on any platform (Mac/Windows/Linux).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Great Android devices coming out this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Easy to do XML way of laying out views.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;SDK can be integrated with Eclipse IDE.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Huge and vibrant developer community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I started learning Android, I thought of doing it from a book rather than learning online. But I quickly gave up the idea, after trying 2 books which were ought to be best out there and they weren&amp;rsquo;t comprehensive enough on many features of Android.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Android structure of views, intents and activities seems intimidating at first sight. But once you start developing an application it becomes definitely shreds that appearance.  The best place to get started for developing in Android is unarguably  &lt;a href=&quot;http://developer.android.com/&quot;&gt;developer.android.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Developer&amp;rsquo;s Guide there explores the concepts behind Android, the framework for  constructing an application, and the tools for developing,  testing, and publishing software for the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the tradition goes, the way to start is by saying &lt;a href=&quot;http://developer.android.com/resources/tutorials/hello-world.html&quot;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://developer.android.com/resources/tutorials/views/index.html&quot;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Hello Views&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; gives an introduction of various views and widgets in Android.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://developer.android.com/resources/tutorials/notepad/index.html&quot;&gt;Notepad Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; This tutorial on developing an Android application gets your feet wet to the framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://developer.android.com/resources/samples/ApiDemos/index.html&quot;&gt;API Demos&lt;/a&gt; illustrate the use of various Android APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://developer.android.com/guide/appendix/faq/commontasks.html&quot;&gt;Common Tasks and How to Do Them in Android&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://groups.google.com/group/android-developers&quot;&gt;Google group  for Android Developers&lt;/a&gt; is the best place to discuss Android Dev.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/&quot;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt; has over 8000 questions tagged Android and you can get answers for most of the questions pertaining to Android Development here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.androidsnippets.org/&quot;&gt;Android Snippets&lt;/a&gt; is where you can share useful snippets of source code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can browse the source code for Android &lt;a href=&quot;http://source.android.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/GoogleDevelopers&quot;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; from recently concluded Google I/O is worth checking out too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of other resources waiting to be exploited all over the Internet for an Android developer. Just get your keywords right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you prefer learning from a book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Beginning-Android-Mark-Murphy/dp/1430224193&quot;&gt;Beginning Android&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Murphy would be my recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the next post onwards, I will post some tutorials based on Application Development in Android.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>primal.pw/android/2010/05/26/first-few-steps-in-android/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">primal.pw/android/2010/05/26/first-few-steps-in-android/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>